A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Mary E. McClymont FA594
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Mary E. McClymont
1969-2008
Rockefeller Archive Center
McClymont, Mary (Mary E.)
Ford Foundation
FA594
10.25 Cubic Feet 27 letter document boxes
Organizational History
When Susan Berresford became President of the Foundation in 1996, she established a new program structure consisting of three large thematic programs. Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) was one of these three programs. Its overall mission was to help improve government performance and accountability, foster a thriving independent civil society, and promote human rights. It was comprised of two global units: Governance and Civil Society, and Human Rights. In 2009, Peace and Social Justice became the Democracy, Rights and Justice Program.
Scope and Contents
The office files of Mary E. McClymont span from 1969 to 2008, with the bulk of the records date from 1981 to 2008. The files contain extensive information about the Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI). The Initiative studied and documented the Foundation's work in the legal field to promote legal reform, public interest law and access to justice from 1998 to 2001. According to a 1998 memorandum, the purpose of the project was to review past and current Foundation grants in order to guide future programming. The end result was the book, Many Roads to Justice. The book was translated into several languages and distributed to nonprofit organizations around the globe.
The collection contains information about the Comparative Constitutionalism Project. Developed and administered by the Governance unit of Peace and Social Justice, the project studied alternative political arrangements for promoting pluralism in diverse societies. Constitutionalism in Africa (1999-2000) was a focus, as the Foundation's goal was to encourage ethnic harmony without forcing homogenization on autonomous cultures and communities.
The collection also contains McClymont's chronological correspondence files from 1988-1990 and program officer memos from Peace and Social Justice program staff.
Other files pertain to grantees or Foundation policy. The files related to the Learning Enhancements Fund are particularly illustrative in regards to Foundation policy. They document the internal Foundation process behind how grant assessments were made, and include a practical guide for program staff files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Arrangement
Arranged into 3 series
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Board of Trustees, 1996-1999
Series 2. Subject Files, 1981-2008
Series 3. Reports, 1969-2008
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rockefeller Archive Center received four accessions of Mary McClymont's files from the Ford Foundation between 2011 and 2020 - Accessions 2011:073, 2012:084, 2019:179, and 2020:017.
- Board of Trustees, 1996-1999; 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  These files contain dockets for meetings of the Board of Trustees. Several of the files also contain handwritten notes, memoranda or discussion papers relating to meetings of the Board or the Board's Audit and Management Committee.
  - Meeting -- Memoranda Re: Development Finance Institutions, Schedule, Discussion Papers, Notes, Background, Docket, 1996 December 11-12 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Meeting -- Docket, 1997 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meeting -- Docket, Schedule, Discussion Paper, Budgets, 1997 June 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Meeting -- Presentation, Docket, 1997 September 24-26 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Meeting -- Docket, Schedule, Reference Memos, 1998 January 28-29 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Meeting -- Docket, Discussion Papers, 1998 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Meeting -- Docket, Memoranda Re: Meeting Agenda, 1998 September 23 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Meeting -- Schedule, Recommendation Memo, Budget Information, 1999 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Meeting -- Docket Parts I and II, List of Grant Actions, 1999 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Meeting -- Audit and Management Committee -- Memoranda Re: Agenda, Discussion Paper on Philippines, Background and Docket, 1999 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- Subject Files, 1981-2008; 2; 8.73 Cubic Feet 23 letter document boxes
  Mary McClymont kept subject files on grantees and grant projects, Ford Foundation policy, and areas where Foundation policy directly impacted grant projects, such as Foundation support for affirmative action. This series also contains chronological correspondence files from 1988-1990 and program officer memos from Peace and Social Justice program staff.
  Arrangement
  The beginning of the series is arranged alphabetically. The subject files in this series received by the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2019 and 2020 were added following the alphabetical materials and is arranged as received.
  - Affirmative Action -- Ford Foundation Support for Affirmative Action, Background, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Africa Human Rights Meeting -- Memoranda Re: Refugees, Correspondence, Notes, Report, 1997 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - American Bar Association World Justice Project -- Correspondence, Notes, Project Information, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Articles on Foundations and Conservatism, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Articles on Globalization (with notes), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Atlantic Philanthropies Meeting -- Notes, Memoranda, Correspondence, and Background on Anti-Terrorism and Human Rights Grants, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Berresford, Susan -- Speeches, Articles, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Berresford, Susan -- Transition Plans -- Memoranda, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Biennial Representatives and Directors Meeting -- Notes, Meeting Book, 1997 February 24-28 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Budget and Financial Analysis Network (BFAN) Learning Group -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Public Budgeting as a Grant Making Area, 1999 December 10-2000 August 11 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Center for the Advancement of Women -- Correspondence, Notes, Reports and Background on Grants, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Central American Initiative Grantee Meeting -- Background, Memoranda, etc., 1996 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - China -- Judicial Reform Feedback Proposal -- Memoranda Re: Observers Group Evaluations, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - China -- Legal Education and Research, 1987 July (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Civil Society Research Project -- Concept Paper, Correspondence Re: Project, Notes, etc., 1997 July 9-1999 March 24 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Collaborative Community Organizing Evaluation -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Background, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Comparative Constitutionalism Project -- Working Papers, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 31-32, Box 5, Folder 33-38)
  - Comparative Human Relations Initiative -- Southern Education Foundation -- Narrative Report, Related Memoranda, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Constitutionalism in Africa -- Reports, Program Officer Memos, Background, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Constitutionalism in Africa Conference, Abuja, Nigeria -- Program, Fact Sheet, Working Papers, 1999 October 5 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Consultant -- Juarez, Roberto -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Latino Review, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Consultant -- Tendler, Judith -- Correspondence, Memoranda Re: Government Programs Consultancy, 1997 December 16-1998 September 18 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Cuba Meeting -- Notes, Agenda, Participants List, 1999 March (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) - Program Review -- Andean Region and Southern Cone, 1981-1990 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) - Program Review -- Cairo FY 1982-1996, 1981-1995 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) - Program Review -- Human Rights and Social Justice Program -- Rapporteur's Notes, 1982-1995 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) - Program Review -- Latin America and the Caribbean FY 1983-1996, 1982-1995 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Developing Countries Program (DCP) - Program Review -- New York-Africa FY 1982-1989, 1981-1988 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Devolution Initiative National Meeting, Birmingham, Alabama -- Meeting Book, 1999 November 17-19 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Eastern Europe -- Clinical Legal Education in the Czech Republic and Slovakia, 1995 March 21 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Eastern Europe -- Evaluation of Ford Foundation Grant Making -- Status of Women in Russia, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Eastern Europe -- Sustainable Funding for Russian NGOs, 2000 August (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Economic and Social Rights Learning Group -- Proposal, Memoranda and Notes on Proposed Learning Group, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Evaluating Legal Services Programs -- Memoranda, 1983 November 2 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Ford Foundation Civil Liberties Program -- Overview of Current Interests, 1985 November 6 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Ford Foundation Human Rights Meeting, Benjamin Hotel, New York -- Meeting Book, 1999 October 25-27 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Galing Pook Foundation -- Transition Documents, Narrative Report, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Garling, Marguerite -- Transition Memo, 1997 April 14 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Background -- Memoranda Re: Updates, Notes, 1998 March 23-1999 March 8 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Board Presentation -- Agenda, Program, Speaking Notes, 2000 September 27 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Brazil Proposal -- Correspondence, 2000 May 17-November 17 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Case Study Plans -- Meeting Notes, Correspondence, 1998 April 10-1999 March 29 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Correspondence from Many Roads to Justice Book Recipients, 1999 October 8-2000 October 13 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Dissemination External Meetings -- Meeting Notes, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Dissemination Plan -- Many Roads to Justice Memoranda, 2000 February 29-2001 August 15 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- East Africa Study -- Correspondence, Notes and Background on Study of Legal Training in Africa, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Indonesia -- Correspondence Re: Book Translation, 2001 January 25-29 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) - Meeting Presentation, 2000 June 22 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Memoranda Re: Purpose, Scope and Plan, Background, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Middle East -- Correspondence Re: Book Distribution, 2000 November 1-2001 February 7 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Miscellaneous -- Program Description, Correspondence, Meeting Agenda, etc., 1998 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Presentation -- Memoranda Re: Staff Question and Answer with Meeting Information, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Rienner, Lynne -- Correspondence Re: Publication of Many Roads to Justice, 1999 September 24-2000 March 24 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Russia -- Correspondence Re: Moscow Office Book Dissemination, 2000 January 22-2001 August 15 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Southern Cone -- Book Dissemination Proposal, Notes, 2000 July-October (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Survey -- Correspondence, 1998 February 11-13 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Translation -- Correspondence and Notes Re: Book Translation, 2000 June 19-September 15 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Trustee Committee Session -- Memoranda, Agenda, Background, 2000 September 27 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Website Memoranda and Background, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- World Bank Gender Law Workshop -- Background, 2000 November 27-30 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Global Law Programs Learning Initiative (GLPLI) -- Workshop on Goals Setting and Indicator Development for PSJ Program Officers -- Agenda, Workshop Materials, 1999 February 5 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Global HIV Initiative Learning Exchange, Pilanesburg, South Africa -- Meeting Book, Notes, Background, 2008 April 1 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Global Security Learning Group -- Notes, Memoranda Summarizing Group Discussions, 1998 August 7-1999 December 7 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Governance -- Africa Economic Research Consortium -- Evaluation, 1997 August 13 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Governance -- Arnold, David -- Program Papers, 1985 June-1997 January 24 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Governance -- Innovations -- Manila Meeting Memorandum Re: Galing Pook Program, 1997 June 16 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Governance and Civil Society Worldwide Meeting, Sao Paolo, Brazil -- Agenda, Notes, Handouts, 2007 October 29-November 2 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Grant Action List, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Human Rights and Social Justice -- Memorandum Re: Legal Aid Field in Middle East, DAGs, etc., 1981 August 7 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Human Rights Meeting -- Notes, Background, 2007 November (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - India -- Governance Program -- Material from New Delhi Office, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - International Cooperation -- South Asia Regional Security and Cooperation Program -- Current Interests, 1997 February (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - International Relations (IR) Admin -- Background Information and Correspondence Re: Ford Foundation Grantees, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - International Rescue Committee -- Meeting Notes, Background, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Presidential Endowment Grant, Grant Information, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Lagos Visit -- Briefing Book, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Learning -- Articles -- Anna Kendrick Reports on Ford Foundation Institutional Learning and Role of Evaluation in Forestry Work, 1985-1995 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Learning -- Background -- Memoranda Re: Transition, Grant Close-Out Evaluations, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Learning -- Memos to the Field -- Learning Group Updates, 1997-1999 (Box 10, Folder 100-101)
  - Learning -- Program Officer Ideas -- Handwritten Notes, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Learning -- Summaries/To Do -- Notes and Memoranda on Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Learning Groups, 1998 July 28-1999 December 15 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Affirmative Action in Israel Memo, 2001 July 23 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Budgeting and Rights Mexico Meeting -- Memoranda, 2001 July 23-25 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Civil Society Consultation -- Workshops Request, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Colombia Initiative -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Peace Seminar, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- East Africa Review of Women's Rights -- Correspondence, 2000 November 15-2001 August 2 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Evaluation -- Memoranda and Notes on How to Conduct Evaluations, 1997-1999 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Governance in East Africa -- Correspondence Re: Study, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Indigenous Human Rights Training Programs -- Funds Request Memo, 2001 April 12 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- International Refugee Program Review -- Correspondence, Memoranda, 2000 December 6-2001 January 17 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Judicial Court Reform in China -- Review Memo, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Labor Mobility in China -- Review Consultancy, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Leadership/International Cooperation -- Funds Request, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Proposals -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Funding, 1999 October 28-2001 August 15 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Learning Enhancement Fund (LEF) -- Study of Ford Foundation Human Rights Funding -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Budget, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Learning Organization Handout -- Drafts, Notes, Correspondence, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Learning Organizations -- Notes, Background, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Learning Protocol -- Cairo -- Protocol, Correspondence, 1999 November 23-December 2 (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Learning Sessions -- Meeting Notes and Materials, Memorandum on PSJ Learning Mechanisms, 2000 December (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - LOGO (Local Governance) Learning Group -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Workshop, Notes, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - Management Assistance Group -- Correspondence Re: Grant Extension, Background, 2005-2007 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - NAACP -- Correspondence and Notes on Meeting, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - National Council of Churches -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Meeting with Ford Foundation Staff, Background, 2000 August 31-November 8 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Nigeria Trip -- Correspondence, Conference Information, Background Papers, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - NGO Monitor's Report -- Correspondence Re: Israel Boycott, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Nonprofit Leadership Initiative Advisory Group Meeting, Los Angeles, CA -- Meeting Notes, Background, 2007 October 23 (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - Orientation -- Grant Maker Handbook, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Orientation -- Grant Maker Handbook, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Field Meetings and Program Learning Groups -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Meetings, 1999 March 30-December 7 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Field Statements, 1998-1999 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Field Statements -- Human Rights, International Cooperation, 1999 January-February (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Field Statements -- Human Rights Programming, 2000 (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Organization Chart, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Police Reform Program -- Correspondence Re: Indonesian Police Watch, 2000 November 14-2001 May 9 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Program Descriptions -- Field Statements, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Program Orientation for Louis Ubias -- Initiatives, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Program Overview and Mission Statement, 1996 September 15 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Restructuring -- Memoranda, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Staff Retreat -- Agenda, Notes, Background Memos, 1997 January (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Staff Retreat -- Portfolio Descriptions and Budgets, 1997 January (Box 12, Folder 142, Box 13, Folder 143)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Staff Retreat -- Notes, Correspondence, Agenda, Background, 1997 November (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Background Conversations -- Correspondence Re: Agenda Planning, Arranging a Speaker, 2000 January 3-April 30 (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Discussions on Proposed Agenda, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Notes, Memoranda, Follow Up, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Preparations -- Speech, Outline, PowerPoint, 2000 June 20 (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting, Krakow, Poland -- Meeting Book, 2000 June 4-9 (Box 13, Folder 149-150)
  - Peace, Equity and Governance Cluster -- Structured Staffing -- Memoranda Re: Reorganization, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - Police -- Articles -- Reports on Meetings, Memoranda Re: Articles, Reference, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - Police -- Assessment Resource Center -- Notes and Correspondence Re: Grant, 2007 (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - Police -- Descriptions of Current Ford Foundation Programming, 1998 February (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Police -- Funds from Peace and Social Justice (PSJ)/Office of Vice President (OVP) Budget -- Memoranda, 2000 November 2-2001 January 10 (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Program Learning Groups -- Update Memos, 1997 February 20-1999 December 21 (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - Right to Health (UN Conference) -- Meeting Book, 2008 April 30 (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - Rights and Social Justice Program Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa -- Meeting Book, 1993 May 23-25 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Robinson, Mary -- Memorandum with Comments on Ethical Globalization Initiative, 2008 January 11-February 15 (Box 14, Folder 159)
  - Sexuality and Reproductive Health Meeting, Johannesburg, South Africa -- Meeting Book, 2008 March 26-28 (Box 14, Folder 160)
  - South Africa -- Follow Up on Discussions of Memo on South Africa and Government/NGO Cooperation, 1995 October 21 (Box 14, Folder 161)
  - South and Southeast Asia -- Hand-Over Memo for the Rights and Social Justice Program in India, Sri Lanka and Nepal, 1996 April 30 (Box 14, Folder 162)
  - Southern Africa -- Grant Evaluation Reports, 1984-1997 (Box 14, Folder 163)
  - Southern Education Foundation -- Proposal, Correspondence Re: Grant, 2006-2007 (Box 14, Folder 164)
  - Thomas, Franklin -- Articles, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 165)
  - Transition -- PSJ Senior Director Post -- Memoranda with Attachments, 2000 November 20 (Box 14, Folder 166)
  - United Nations -- Notes and Background on Fund for International Partnership, Ford Foundation UN-Related Programming, 1995 June 28-2000 February 29 (Box 15, Folder 167)
  - United Nations -- UN High Commissioner for Refugees -- Dennis McNamara Testimony, Information on Refugees, 1998 October 8-1999 August 2 (Box 15, Folder 168)
  - United Nations and World Bank Meetings -- Notes, 2000 September-October (Box 15, Folder 169)
  - U.S. Social Forum -- Correspondence Re: IIE, Notes, Grant Information, Background, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 170)
  - Vector Project -- Memoranda, Meeting Notes, 1997-1998 (Box 15, Folder 171)
  - Vector Project -- Papers -- Project Work Binder, 1997-1998 (Box 15, Folder 172)
  - Vector Project -- Working File -- Correspondence, Memoranda, 1998-2000 (Box 15, Folder 173)
  - Vera Institute -- Grant Recommendations, Correspondence, Background, 2000-2001 (Box 15, Folder 174)